Finding Aid for Ralph Stone Papers, 1882-1956
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ralph Stone papers 1882-1956
Stone, Ralph, 1868-1956.
3 oversize volumes
4 linear feet
8691 Aa 2; AC
Detroit banker, alumnus and regent of the University of Michigan; contain correspondence and other papers largely concerning University affairs, including athletics, the Development Council, alumni activities, regental affairs; also papers concerning Detroit city government, Detroit Street Railways, affairs of the Alien Property Custodian in World War I, recollections of University life in 1890's,articles on Hazen S. Pingree and Chase S. Osborn; also scrapbooks, speeches, manuscripts, and genealogical material.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was largely donated by Ralph Stone (donor no. 1981 ) in multiple accessions, 1944-1955. Miscellaneous other materials came from the U-M Development Council (donor no. 3576 ).
The collection is open to research.
Ralph Stone was born in Wilmington, Delaware, November 20, 1868. He was graduated from Swarthmore College in 1889, then from the University of Michigan Law School in 1892. At the U-M, Stone was a member of the first editorial staff of the Michigan Daily and editor-in-chief of the Michigan Law Journal. In succeeding years Stone was active in alumni affairs and fundraising. He was trustee of the Alumni Fund from its incorporation in 1920 until 1941.
He began practicing law in Grand Rapids in 1892. The next year he was appointed trust officer of the Michigan Trust Company of Grand Rapids. On January 1, 1899, he was appointed private secretary to Governor Hazen S. Pingree. After serving briefly as a state bank examiner, he was appointed assistant secretary of the newly organized Detroit Trust Co. He was president of the Detroit Trust Co. from 1915 to 1927 and chairman of the board from 1927 to 1933. Thereafter was consultant to the company until he retired in 1945.
During World War I, Stone was director of the Bureau of Trusts of the Alien Property Custodian in Washington DC. He was also president of the Detroit Bureau of Governmental Research, a trustee of the Cranbrook Foundation, and treasurer of the Liberty Loan Committee of Detroit and Wayne County.
Stone served two eight-year terms as Regent of the University of Michigan, from 1924 to 1940
He died in May 11, 1956.
The Stone collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Speeches and Articles; Subject Files; and Clipping and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Banks and banking--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.); Detroit United Railway.; Municipal government--Michigan--Detroit.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Pingree, Hazen S., 1840-1901.; Street-railroads--Michigan--Detroit.; United States. Alien Property Custodian.; University of Michigan. Alumni Association.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. Development Council.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; World War, 1914-1918.
Contributors:
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - Regarding Stone's entrance to the University of Michigan 1890-1891 (Box 1)
  - Concerning the Advisory Board of the University Athletic Association 1893 (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence
    - 1900-1910 (Box 1)
    - 1928-1931 (Box 1)
    - 1932-1934 (Box 1)
    - 1935-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1940-1943 (Box 1)
    - 1944 (Box 1)
    - 1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951 (Box 1)
    - 1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
- Speeches and Articles
  - "From the Old Scrapbook" 1890-1892 (Box 1)
    (reminiscences of extracurricular activities at the University of Michigan)
  - History of the University of Michigan Detroit alumni groups (Box 1)
  - ''Who was Ruth Waldo?" (Box 1)
    (Genealogical sketch of the Stone family)
  - "Recollections of the University of Michigan Alumni Fund'' (Box 1)
  - "Liberty loan committee for Detroit and Wayne County in World War I.'' (Box 1)
  - "Hazen Pingree, the man-not a statue.'' (Box 1)
- Subject Files
  - Detroit Street Railways 1899, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Student publications at the University of Michigan 1893 (Box 1)
  - Development Council at the University of Michigan 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Fund and the Development Council 1943-1953, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Intercollegiate Athletic Association of the Northwest 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Bureau of Governmental Research 1947-1954 (Box 1)
  - Cranbrook Music Project 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - 60th reunion of the 1892 law class, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Semi-centennial of the Michigan Daily 1940 (Box 2)
  - Advisory Committee on the sale of alien property, minutes 1918-1920 (Box 2)
  - Work of the Advisory Committee, memorandum 1920 (Box 2)
  - Michigan state deficit 1953 (Box 2)
  - Charles E. Wilson's sale of General Motors stock before becoming Secretary of Defense 1953 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Clippings and Scrapbooks
  - Newspaper clippings 1887-1893 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1889 (Box 2)
      (Subjects: Delaware politics, "Subsidies to American Ships" by George W. Stone; some clippings about Ralph Stone)
    - 1892-1893 (Box 2)
      (Subjects: Ann Arbor -- baseball; Grand Rapids Herald editorials, law practice, and tennis)
    - 1895-1898 (Box 2)
      (Subjects: Grand Rapids -- politics -- marriage of Ralph Stone and Mary Jeffords -- New York Bar Association speech -- letters to editor written anonymously by RS for Gas and Electric Co. -- Michigan Trust Co.)
    - April-May 1899 (Box 2)
      (Subjects: Governor Hazen Pingree era)
    - May-July 1899 (Box 2)
    - July 13-29, 1899 (Box 3)
    - July-December 1899 (Box 3)
    - February-December 1900 (Box 3)
    - February 1901-October 1910 (Box 3)
      (Subjects: Pingree's death, Detroit Trust Co. -- miscellaneous trust companies -- sports-addresses)
    - February 1911-December 1915 (Box 4)
      (Subjects: father mayor of Santa Cruz, Calif. -- tennis championship in Detroit -- trust co.)
    - 1915-1919 (Box 4)
      (Subjects: Detroit Trust Co. -- Liberty Loans -- Alien Property Custodian)
    - 1917 (Box 4)
      (Subjects: Alien Property Custodian)
    - 1919-1921 (Box 4)
      (Subjects: mother's death -- Amy Stone's stories -- first University of Michigan Alumni Fund started -- daughter Ruth's and Henry Caulkins' wedding)
    - 1921-1931
      (oversize volume)
      (Almost entirely Detroit Trust Co. matters-sale of Lincoln Motor Co. to Henry Ford-Election as Regent of U of M-Magazine Articles and Addresses-Death of Father, March 19, 1923 -- 32 page Report on First Alumni Fund U of M-Dodge Sale-25th Anniversary of the Trust Co.-Addition of 100 feet front to present office of Detroit Trust Co.-Report to Mayor Lodge on Street Railways-Organization of Detroit Bankers Co.-Committee on City Finances, Ralph Stone, Chairman-Ralph Stone elected 2nd term as Regent U of M)
    - 1929-1948 (Volume 1)
      (50th Anniversary of The Michigan Trust Co.-Photos Birmingham home from Better Homes and Gardens-completion of 2nd term as Regent U of M-50th Anniversary Michigan Daily with speech-Copy first article, Vol. I, No. 1, in Michigan Alumnus by Ralph Stone: "The Alumni Question-A Review"-Photo Ralph Stone with Tony Trabert (National Tennis Champion 1953) as player national boys tournament at Cranbrook-Review by "The Commentator" W. K. Kelsey in Detroit News of article by Ralph Stone, "Enemy Property in Two World Wars," in Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review-Ralph Stone awarded "Scott Medal for Distinguished Alumni Service")
    - 1947-1953 (Volume 2)
      (More about above Medal for Distinguished Alumni Service, U of M Photo of first staff of U of M Daily 1890-92-Copy first page U of M Daily, September 29, 1890-marriage of grandson Ralph Stone Caulkins to Beverley Cordner-50th Anniversary Detroit Trust Co.-Photo Swarthmore College Orchestra of 1886 Ralph Stone 'cello-Speech before Detroit Historical Society by Ralph Stone on "Hazen S. Pingree, The Man-Not a Statue"-History by Ralph Stone of U of M Alumni Association of Detroit)
    - 1882-1890 of George W. Stone (Box 4)
      (Excerpt of Stone's note: Scrapbook kept by my Father George W. Stone, a merchant (large establishment, engines, boilers, saw mills, oils, ship chandlery, plumbing supplies, electric goods) then Treasurer, American Unitarian Association, ordained as a minister by Reverend Edward Everett Hale and others, minister at Kansas City, Field Secretary (equivalent to Bishop in other denominations) in charge of all Unitarian Churches west of Rocky Mountains, retired to become minister of Church of Santa Cruz, Calif., and Mayor of Santa Cruz and a member of the California State Board of Education for two terms by appointment of Governor Hiram Johnson. Scrapbook contains editorials by him in Wilmington (Del.) Morning News, many letters to the editor, addresses on various subjects, many on subsidies to American shipping (he was Secretary for Delaware of the American Shipping & Industrial League., lectures on various subjects, politics in Delaware. He was Judge Advocate in the North Atlantic Squadron during the Civil War on Admiral Porter's staff, blockading the Atlantic Coast, etc. He lectured in the large armory at Hampton Roads, Va., during the Civil War, on the Constitution of the United States to as many as 2000 in the audiences of soldiers and sailors at Fortress Monroe. He was the first to board the "Monitor" (with a fellow officer) after its battle with the Confederate "Merrimac." He had just been admitted to the bar of Cortland County, New York.)